Inventory of the University of Hawaii collection
Hoover Institution Archives
University of Hawaii collection
1944-1945
XX232
28 envelopes (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs depicting World War II campaigns in France and Germany, activities of American troops, and Allied military and civilian leaders. Collected by the University of Hawaii.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photographs depicting World War II campaigns in France and Germany, activities of American troops, and Allied military and civilian leaders. Collected by the University of Hawaii.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Western Front.; World War, 1939-1945--Pictorial works.; University of Hawaii.
Collection Contents
- 92 prints relating to World War II military operations of the U.S. expeditionary forces in France., June 1944- (Folder A)
- 29 prints depicting World War II various activities of the U.S. expeditionary forces in France, including prints of Allied supplies flowing into restored port of Le Havre; Allied tugs towing prebuilt harbors to Normandy coast; a U.S. "lost battalion" being relieved., undated (Folder B)
- 14 prints depicting U.S. troops liberating civilians and allied soldiers imprisoned by Nazis in France during World War II., undated (Folder C)
- 52 prints relating to World War II military operations of the French troops in France and in Germany, and the French Flyers fighting German from home bases., 1944-1945 (Folder D)
- 22 prints depicting German officers and soldiers being made prisoners in France; dead German soldiers and German material damage in France., 1944 (Folder E)
- 36 prints depicting French civilians in France., 1944 (Folder F)
- 18 prints relating to the distribution of U.S. supplies and food to the French population and depicting sick people with nurses., 1944 (Folder G)
- 13 prints relating to trials and executions of French collaborationists at the end of the war in France., undated (Folder H)
- 21 prints relating to the "rebirth of a French town," Laval, gradually getting back to normal life after its liberation by American forces on August 6, 1944, and depicting Laval's population at work., undated (Folder I)
- 13 prints depicting U.S. soldiers and French rail men reviving Paris railway yard "Les Batignolles"., 1944 (Folder J)
- 44 prints relating to Armistice Day ceremonies held in Paris and other cities, on November 11, 1944, particularly in the Forest of Compiègne, where Hitler signed the June 1940 armistice with France, on the same spot where the last armistice was concluded, November 11, 1918; various ceremonies in France celebrating liberation by American forces, or commemorating dead soldiers of World War I, as well as prints relating to the ceremonies honoring the 101st U.S. Airborne Division, in France, March 15, 1945. (Folder K)
- 23 prints relating to the reopening of the Louvre Museum in Paris, after the city's liberation by American forces, August 1944; the Pasteur Institute in Paris cooperating with the U.S. Army and other miscellaneous prints, including the Luxembourg Palace in Paris, after its evacuation by the Germans. (Folder L)
- 103 prints relating to World War II military operations of the U.S. expeditionary forces advancing in Germany., undated (Folder M)
- 56 prints relating to the crossing of the Moselle river in Germany by the Third U.S. Army, March 17, 1945, and to the crossing of the Roer river in Germany by the Ninth U.S. Army on a large scale offensive launched on February 23, 1945. (Folder N)
- 68 prints relating to the U.S. military operations on crossing the Rhine river in Germany, with prints of the Ludendorff Bridge at Remagen, seized March 7, 1945 by the First U.S. Army; the crossing of the Rhine river by the Ninth U.S. Army, March 23, 1945; The U.S. Navy ferrying troops and heavy equipment across the Rhine and the greatest airborne offensive of the war launched March 24, 1945. (Folder O)
- 75 prints depicting U.S. troops entering major German cities: Dusseldorf, Cologne, Bonn, Coblenz, Worms, Frankfurt, Heidelberg, Hanover, Munich, Berlin, including prints of Hitler's "Berghof" near Berchtesgaden and general views of Bremen, Hamburg, and Mannheim., 1944-1945 (Folder P)
- 102 prints depicting U.S. troops entering small German towns., 1944-1945 (Folder Q)
- 19 prints relating to the bombing of German plants and the taking over of others almost intact by the U.S. forces in Germany., 1944-1945 (Folder R)
- 25 prints depicting American soldiers on respite from battle, and others either wounded or dead in Germany., 1944-1945 (Folder S)
- 42 prints depicting German prisoners of war and dead soldiers, in Germany., 1944-1945 (Folder T)
- 88 prints depicting German civilians in Germany., 1944-1945 (Folder U-V)
- 37 prints, depicting military operations on other European fronts; Russian troops moving westwards, 1945; various slogans painted on walls in Germany; Munich in 1937; Austria's Chancellor Engelbert Dollfuss, who was assassinated by Austrian Nazis in 1934, lying in state in Vienna. (Folder W)
- 76 prints depicting important military and political leaders such as Franklin D. Roosevelt, Dwight D. Eisenhower; George C. Marshall; Winston C. Churchill; Joseph Stalin; Andrei Gromyko; Charles de Gaulle; Henri Honoré Giraud, undated (Folder X)
- 131 prints depicting American, British, and Australian generals, including prints of Harold R.L.G. Alexander; Henry H. Arnold; Anthony J. Drexel Biddle; Haydon L. Boatner; Omar N. Bradley; Lewis H. Brereton; Edward H. Brooke; John K. Cannon; Claire L. Chennault; Mark W. Clark; Arthur B. Cook; John R. Deane; Jacob L. Devers; John L. DeWitt; James H. Doolittle., undated (Folder Y-Z)
- 47 prints depicting American political personalities such as Dean G. Acheson; Bernard M. Baruch; Adolph A. Berle, Jr.; Francis Biddle; Sol Bloom; Chester Bowles; Laughlin Currie; Joseph E. Davies; Norman H. Davis; William O. Douglas; James V. Forrestal; Joseph Clark Grew; Fiorello H. LaGuardia., undated (Folder AA)
- 25 miscellaneous prints, depicting U.S. pilots during World War II; Clark Gable, American screen star; Charles Boyer, French screen star; Jane Addams, American social reformer and writer; Senator Benedetto Croce, anti-fascist philosopher; General Costa, Italian fascist officer; General Cramer, German commander of all Axis Panzer armies in North Africa., undated (Folder BB)